Guide to the Mike McGrady papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Mike McGrady papers,
1966-1970.
McGrady, Mike.
1 linear ft. (2 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0823
4079066
The Mike McGrady Papers contain the draft manuscripts, correspondence, memos, and newspaper clippings related to a publishing hoax in 1969, where 26 reporters for Newsday wrote a novel under the penname Penelope Ashe.
Biographical Note
In 1966, three reporters, Mike McGrady, Harvey Aronson, and John Cummings were at a bar on Long Island discussing their opinions of recent best selling authors Harold Robbins and Jacqueline Susann. They agreed that in the literary climate of the 1960s, a book wouldn't sell without sex scenes, and decided that together they could write a bestselling "dirty book." On June 13, 1966, McGrady sent a memo to everyone at Newsday inviting them to write chapters, with details about the main character and a few guidelines for the writers. They were instructed to write chapters of at least 2,500 words, with an emphasis on sex and very bad writing. McGrady wrote the general storyline. The main character, Gillian Blake was part of a husband-and-wife talk radio team and found out her husband cheated. She retaliated by having an affair, and eventually escalated to breaking up all of the marriages in her community.
They intended to write the entire book in a week but it actually took a year. McGrady and Harvey Aronson divided the editing. Once the book was edited, they searched for a woman to play "Penelope Ashe," and settled on McGrady's sister-in-law, she was the right age and appearance, and conveniently looked like Jacqueline Susann. The group decided on Lyle Stuart as publisher, a controversial publisher who had a history of controversial texts, although he had never published a "dirty book." Stuart knew about the hoax from the outset, and was interested in buying the book even without reading it.
Naked Came the Stranger was published in July 1969, with a carefully chosen book jacket and photo and biography of "Penelope Ashe." The book was relatively successful when it first came out, and even though the ad campaign for the book showed photos of the actual authors, only one reviewer, William Trotter at the Charlotte Observer, suspected that the book wasn't written by Penelope Ashe. The reviews for the book were generally bad, but some reviewers thought that it was good for its genre. The book sold well enough that it was eventually issued as a paperback.
The story that it was actually written by twenty-six journalists eventually broke when various news organizations wanted to run the story, and McGrady and the others managed to turn it into front page news by playing them against each other. The book then shot to the top of the New York Times bestseller list, and the real authors promoted their work across the country. Reception to the hoax was mixed, but the response indicates that people thought it was a very clever ruse and still liked the book. A year later, McGrady wrote Stranger Than Naked or How to Write Dirty Books for Fun & Profit, detailing the story behind the book.
Scope and Content
The Mike McGrady collection consists of the drafts and administrative materials surrounding the publishing of Naked Came the Stranger. The collection contains draft manuscripts of Naked Came the Stranger and Stranger than Naked or How to Write Dirty Books for Fun & Profit. The collection also contains correspondence, memos to all of the authors, and newsclippings from the ad campaign and the response to the hoax.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series
Series I. Manuscripts
Series II. Administrative Files
Subjects
Ashe, Penelope.; McGrady, Mike.; Long Island (N.Y.); Literary forgeries and mystifications.; Adultery--Fiction.; Impostors and imposture.; Hoaxes.; Suburban life--Fiction.; Revenge--Fiction.; Journalists.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Newsday (Hempstead, N.Y.)--History.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1970 M-70 McGrady, Mike Gift
- Series I: Manuscripts
  Series I is comprised of the manuscripts of Naked Came the Stranger and Stranger than Naked or How to Write Dirty Books for Fun & Profit. The folders for Naked Came the Stranger contain the original drafts submitted by the various authors, as well as the final drafts as edited by McGrady and Aronson, and the publisher. The second manuscript is McGrady's personal copy that he edited and compiled.
  - Naked Came the Stranger
    - Published work, 1969
    - Mike McGrady--Billy and Gilly, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John Cummings--Ernie Miklos, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - George Vecsey--Morton Earbrow, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jack Schwartz--Joshua Turnbull, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jane Margold--Arthur Franhop, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bob Greene--Mario Vella, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bernie Bookbinder--Marvin Goodman, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Carol Burton, Stan Green--Alan Hetterton, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bob Waters--Paddy Madigan, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bill McIlwain--Taylor Hawkes, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bob Wiemer--Ansel Varth, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Harvey Aronson--Melvin Corby, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gene Goltz, Merle Goldberg--Willoughby Martin, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bob Mayer, Val Duncan, Ken Byerly, Mal Karman--Zoltan Caradoc, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Emmett Brightwell, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Martin Buskin--Reuben Dalrymple, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Anthony Insolia--Charles Luckman, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Barry Abisch--Sheldon Bernstein, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Marilyn Berger--Esther, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Station Breaks, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Stranger Than Naked or How to Write Dirty Books for Fun & Profit, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1 to 2)
- Series II: Administrative files
  Series II contains all of the administrative files related to the hoax. McGrady organized them into different groups, correspondence from the co-authors, correspondence in response to the hoax, memos to the co-authors, the advertising campaign, and newspapers articles describing the hoax. The correspondence from the co-authors concentrates on keeping the hoax a secret after the book was published. They also write about how to manage dividing the profits among 26 people, and the publicity required of everyone once they were revealed. The correspondence in response to the hoax contains letters from friends as well as the general public. Many people wrote to McGrady after the hoax was revealed, most thought that it was very clever, but there are a few letters from people who believed that the project promoted this type of literature instead of criticizing it. The memos to the co-authors are comprised of the original memo proposing the project, as well as follow-up giving more details of the project and the expectations. This series also contains a number of news clippings of the advertising as well as the stories when the hoax broke, and responses to the story in various newspapers.
  - Correspondence from co-authors, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3 to 4)
  - Correspondence in response to hoax, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4 to 5)
  - Memos to the co-authors, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Advertising campaign, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper articles describing the hoax, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9 to 10)
  - Photograph of the co-authors, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)